Chapter 12. Biographical.
Quiqu was a native of Kokavoko, an island far away to the west and south.
It is not down in any map. True places never are. When a new hatched savage,
running wild about his native woodlands in a grass clout, followed by the
nibbling goats as if he were a green sapling. Even then, in Quiqu's ambitious
soul lurked a strong desire to see something more of Christrysendom than a
specimen whaler or two. His father was a high chief, a king, his uncle a high
priest, and on the maternal side he boasted aunts who were the wives of
unconquerable warriors. There was excellent blood in his veins, royal
stuff, though sadly visiated, I fear, by the cannibal propensity he nourished in
his untuded youth. A Sag Harbor ship visited his father's bay, and Quiquake
sought a passage to the Christian lands.
But the ship, having her full compliment of seaman, spurned his suit, and not all
the king his father's influence, could prevail. But Quiquake vowed a vow. Alone
in his canoe, he paddled off to a distant straight, which he knew the ship
must pass through when she quitted the island. On one side was a coral reef, on
the other a low tongue of land covered with mangrove thickets that grew out
into the water. hiding his canoe, still afloat among these thickets, with its
prow seawward, he sat down in the stern, paddle low in hand, and when the ship
was gliding by, like a flash, he darted out, gained her side, and with one
backward dash of his foot, capsized, and sank the canoe, climbed up the chains,
and throwing himself at full length upon the deck, grappled a ringbolt there, and
swore not to let go, though hacked in pieces.
In vain the captain threatened to throw him overboard, suspended a cutless over
his naked wrists. Quiqu was the son of a king, and Quiquag budged not. Struck by
his desperate dauntlessness and his wild desire to visit Christrysendom, the
captain at last relented, and told him he might make himself at home. But this
fine young savage, this sea prince of Wales, never saw the captain's cabin.
They put him down among the sailors and made a whaleman of him. But like Zar
Peter, content to toil in the shipyards of foreign cities, Quiqu disdained no
seeming igniminy, if thereby he might happily gain the power of enlightening
his untoured countrymen. For at bottom, so he told me, he was actuated by a
profound desire to learn among the Christians the arts whereby to make his
people still happier than they were, and more than that, still better than they
were. But alas, the practices of whalemen soon convinced him that even
Christians could be both miserable and wicked, infinitely more so than all his
father's heathens, arrived at last in old Sag Harbor, and seeing what the
sailors did there, and going on to Nantucket, and seeing how they spent
their wages in that place also, poor Quiquay gave it up for lost, thought he,
it's a wicked world in all meridians.
I'll die a pagan. And thus an old idoltor at heart, he yet lived among
these Christians, wore their clothes, and tried to talk their gibberish, hence
the queer ways about him, though now some time from home.
By hence I asked him whether he did not propose going back and having a
coronation, since he might now consider his father dead and gone, he being very
old and feeble at the last accounts. He answered, "No, not yet," and added that
he was fearful Christianity, or rather Christians, had unfitted him for
ascending the pure and undefiled throne of 30 pagan kings before him. But by and
by, he said he would return as soon as he felt himself baptized again. For the
nons, however, he proposed to sail about and sew his wild oats in all four
oceans. They had made a harpooner of him, and that barbed iron was in lie of
a scepter. Now I asked him what might be his immediate purpose touching his
future movements. He answered to go to sea again in his old vocation. Upon this
I told him that whailing was my own design and informed him of my intention
to sail out of Nantucket as being the most promising port for an adventurous
whaleman to embark from. He had once resolved to accompany me to that island,
ship aboard the same vessel, get into the same watch, the same boat, the same
mess with me, in short, to share my every hap, with both my hands and his,
boldly dip into the potluck of both worlds. To all this I joyously asented,
for besides the affection I now felt for Quiquake, he was an experienced
harpooner, and as such could not fail to be of great usefulness to one who, like
me, was wholly ignorant of the mysteries of whailing, though well acquainted with
the sea, as known to merchant seaman.
His story being ended with his pipe's last dying puff, Quequake embraced me,
pressed his forehead against mine, and blowing out the light, we rolled over
from each other this way and that, and very soon were sleeping.